Guide to the Salah Taher Collection AD.MC.107
al Mawrid Arab Art Archive, NYU Abu Dhabi
Salah Taher Collection
1911-2016
al Mawrid Arab Art Archive, NYU Abu Dhabi
Salah Taher (Egyptian Artist, 1911-2007)
Ayman Taher
AD.MC.107
1761 Digital Objects
The Salah Taher Collection consists of exhibition materials, press clippings, radio and television scripts, writings, correspondence, official documents, handwritten reflections, diaries and photographs of his life and work to posthumous exhibitions. Emerging from what is known as the second generation of artists in modern Egyptian art, Salah Taher (1911-2007) stands as a distinguished figure whose artistic journey left an indelible mark on the nation's artistic landscape. Taher studied at the School of Fine Arts in Cairo. Graduating in 1934 and organizing his first solo exhibition the following year in the city of Minya, Taher dedicated the next decade teaching in various schools across Egypt, before securing a professorship at the School of Fine Arts in 1944. Taher held more than 80 local and international exhibitions, with his style moving from academic portraiture to nonrepresentational abstraction. He represented Egypt in major international exhibitions and was awarded many international prizes throughout his career. Taher has also held significant leadership roles in various art institutions, such as the Museum of Modern Art, the director of artistic affairs and cultural management in the office of the Minister of Culture and National Guidance and then director of cultural management and artistic adviser at Al Ahram newspaper. Taher played an important role as an artist and art and culture practitioner, in the Egyptian cultural milieu, from the 1950s to his death in 2007.
The materials were received in good condition, which enabled the digitization to take place at al Mawrid Arab Center for the Study of Art, NYUAD. Digital surrogates were created for all collection items. Upon digitization, all materials were returned to the owner. Materials were rehoused in archival enclosures as needed.
E-records AD_MC_107
Scope and Contents
The Salah Taher Collection consists of the personal and professional papers of the artist, such as birth and death certificates, address books, and work contracts, as well as more than seventy small format diaries kept by the artist, who recorded his thoughts on life, art, spirituality, among other topics. Fourteen draft scripts from the television program Min ʻĀlam al-Funūn [From the World of the Arts] are also included, as well as various other writings by the artist. The collection also includes exhibition materials, press clippings of articles written by the artist and about the artist starting from the 1960s, as well as letters received by Taher.
This archive comprises several sets of photographs, negatives and slides of Salah Taher, his family life, friends and other intellectuals in his social and professional circle, as well as images of artwork, exhibition openings, work gatherings, and models. Some photographs, negatives and slides were arranged by the artist himself and have been kept as such.
Materials in the collection span seven decades from Taher's birth in 1911 to posthumous exhibitions and offer context and insight into Taher's artistic and cultural milieu in Egypt, where he was based, as well as his regional and international connections. The majority of the material is in Arabic, although exhibition materials are often bilingual, in Arabic and either French or English.
Biographical Note
Salah El Din Taher Mohamed Abdeldayem (1911-2007), better known as Salah Taher, belongs to what is sometimes known as the "second generation" of artists in modern Egyptian art. A distinguished figure whose career featured numerous high appointments in the national cultural infrastructure, Taher's artistic journey left an indelible mark on the artistic landscape of the country. His style of painting underwent many changes throughout his life. In his early years, Taher was known for his academic portraits and landscapes. Later, in the 1960s, a transformative experience during a visit to the United States prompted him to shift to nonrepresentational abstraction. Using tools such as knives and combs to depict his subjects, he abandoned descriptive trends and focused on conveying his philosophy on spirituality, and interpreting music and literature in a visual art. Taher became known for his experiments with unusual tools for manipulating paint, employing a vast array of instruments such as combs, spatulas, rakes, solvents, and other devices to work in oil, watercolors, gouache, and acrylic.
Taher was born in Cairo to a family of Syrian origins who worked in the textile trade. He studied at the School of Fine Arts in Cairo and was mentored by the prominent artists Ahmed Sabri (1889-1955), Camillo Innocenti (1871–1961) and Roger Bréval (dates unknown). Graduating in 1934 and organizing his first solo exhibition the following year in the city of Minya, Taher dedicated the next decade to teaching in various schools in Minya, Alexandria and Cairo, before securing a professorship at the School of Fine Arts in 1944. From the mid-1940s to the beginning of the 1950s, Taher continued his artistic exploration within the vibrant artistic haven of "Al Marsam," the collective of studios established by Sheikh Ali Abdel Rassoul in the New Gourna village in Luxor, there forging a friendship with its designer, the architect Hassan Fathy (1900-1989).
Returning to Cairo in 1954, Taher assumed a number of leadership roles. He served as Director of the Museum of Modern Egyptian Art for four years. In 1959, he became director in the office of the Minister of Culture and National Guidance and then director of the fine arts department in 1961, within the same ministry. He gave lectures at the Institute of Cinema, 1961 to 1965, and became the Director of the Khedivial Opera House (1962-1966). In 1963, he joined a group of artists sent by the Ministry of Culture to record impressions of the construction of the High Dam and ensuing resettlement of the people of Nubia. In 1965, he was awarded a grant by UNESCO, which supported travel for six months and allowed him to meet such artists as Henry Moore and the art critic John Russell. In 1966, Taher was appointed artistic adviser at Al Ahram newspaper, a position he held up until his death in 2007, and during which he wrote more than 250 articles. Taher was also commissioned to produce several murals and 35 large paintings that are today part of the Al Ahram collection.
In 1980, Taher became a member and chairman of the artistic committee of the Supreme Council of Culture, the Chairman of the Art Committee of the National Specialized Councils, and head of the Société des Amis de l'Art, holding the latter post from 1984 until his death.
The artist was a close friend and mentee of the Egyptian journalist, poet and literary critic Abbas Mahmoud Aqqad (1889-1964) from the early 1930s until the death of Aqqad in 1964. Aqqad bequeathed an extensive library to the artist that went on to greatly shape his thinking. Taher counted writers, critics, artists, such as Tawfiq al Hakim, Umm Kulthum, Ihsan Abd el Koddous, Anis Mansour, Kamal Mallakh, Naguib Mahfouz, Zakariyya Ahmed, Adam Henein and Tharwat Okasha, among his circle, many of whom he painted portraits of.
Taher was an avid reader and music aficionado, his diverse interests included philosophy and psychology. He practiced boxing and even acted in a film. Throughout his life, Taher maintained small size notebooks, where he wrote his thoughts on many subjects such as spirituality, Sufism, the importance of yoga and meditation, among other reflections, which in turn find expression in his paintings. Taher also experimented with Arabic calligraphy, creating a series entitled "Huwwa," converging his love for the Arabic letter and his interest in Sufism.
Taher had more than eighty local and international exhibitions. He participated in the Egypt Pavilion at the Venice Biennale (1952, 1956, 1958, 1962 and 1966), and participated in the Alexandria Biennale in 1961, where he was awarded the first prize for painting. In 1959, he won Egypt's State Encouragement Prize for oil painting and the Guggenheim Award in 1960. In 1974, Taher was awarded the State Prize of Merit for Art and the Medal of Science and Arts. In 1999, he became the first artist to win the Mubarak Award for Arts, Literature, and Social Science, now known as The Nile Award.
Taher passed away in Cairo on February 6, 2007.
Ayman Taher
Artist Ayman Taher (1946-) was mentored by his father Salah Taher (1911-2007) who organized his first exhibition at the age of 12. Having graduated from the School of Fine Arts in 1970, Ayman Taher decided to study underwater photography and diving, in order to break away from his father's legacy. He lived between Cairo, Hurghada, and Sharm El Sheikh, and exhibited his photographic works in Egypt, at the Louvre Museum in France and at the Carnegie Museum of Art and the Brooks Institute of Photography in California, now known as the Brooks Institute. Ayman Taher contributed photographs to several books including Sinai: the Site and the History published by the New York University Press in 1995.
Ayman Taher returned to painting in 2006 and has held numerous exhibitions in Egypt, often exhibiting his work in parallel with the work of Salah Taher
Custodial History
These materials are part of the family estate of Salah Taher (1911-2007). The collection is in the custody of his only son, Ayman Taher (1946-). The artist lived in Giza throughout his life, and moved to his son Ayman's house in the district of Sheikh Zayed towards the end of his life, moving with him all of his belongings. The collection is located on Ayman's property, some materials are in his residence, others are in his studio adjacent to the main residence.
Some folders were organized by the artist himself, such as folders with newspaper articles. Boxes of negatives were also assembled and organized by the artist. The rest of the collection was arranged by al Mawrid's team.
Conditions Governing Access
Digital surrogates only are held by the repository. Based on the agreement with the owner, digital images of selected series/subseries will be publicly available on the NYU Archival Collections Finding Aid Portal. Materials not made available online may be consulted in person at al Mawrid, NYUAD. Researchers should contact nyuad.almawrid@nyu.edu to request details or to make an appointment.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in the following series: (I) Personal and Professional Papers; (II) Writings; (III) Correspondence; (IV) Exhibition Materials; (V) Press Clippings; (VI) Photographic Materials; (VII) Other Items in the Possession of the Artist.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was borrowed from the artist's only son Ayman Taher, digitized at al Mawrid NYUAD and returned to the owner.
Related Materials
The American University in Cairo has a parallel collection of papers that was donated by the artist's son Ayman Taher after his father's death. See Guide to the Salah Taher Personal Papers Collection, 1950s-2000s (in process), University Archives, Rare Books and Special Collections Library, The American University in Cairo, https://lib.aucegypt.edu/record=b1583851~S2
Existence and Location of Originals
The original material is in the possession of Ayman Taher, in his property in Cairo, Egypt.
Bibliography
1. Abaza, Mona. Twentieth-Century Egyptian Art. Cairo: American University in Cairo Press, 2011.
2. Al Attar, Mokhtar. Ruwwād al Fann wa al Tanwīr fī Miṣr wa al ʿAlam al ʿArabī. Cairo: The Egyptian General Book Authority, 2009.
3. Azar, Aimé. La Peinture Moderne en Égypte. Cairo: Les Editions Nouvelles, 1961.
4. El Razzaz, Mostafa. Al Fann al Miṣrī al Ḥadīth al Qarn al ʿIshrūn. Cairo: Egyptian Ministry of Culture, 2007.
5. Hamza, Jylan. Salah Taher: Faylasufu al-Alwan. Cairo: The Egyptian General Book Authority, 1999.
6. Karnouk, Liliane. Contemporary Egyptian Art. Cairo: American University in Cairo Press, 1995.
7. Mutwalli, Midhat, and Fathi Husayn. Salah Taher: Painting. Alexandria: Bibliotheca Alexandrina, 2001.
8. Naguib, Ezz El-Din. Al Fanan al-Miṣrī wa Sūʾalu al-Hāwīyat. Cairo: DAI Art Gallery, 2022.
9. Sharuni, Subhi. Salah Taher. Cairo: State Information Service, 1985.
Art, Abstract; Art -- Arab countries -- الفن -- الدول العربية; Art, Arab -- 20th century -- الفن العربي -- القرن العشرين; Art--Arab countries--20th century--Exhibitions; Art, Arab -- الفن العربي; Art archives -- أرشيفات الفن; Art, Egyptian; Art, Egyptian -- Exhibitions; Art, Egyptian -- 20th century; Painting, Egyptian -- 20th century; Cairo (Egypt); Minyā (Egypt); Luxor (Egypt); Alexandria (Egypt); Salah Taher (Egyptian Artist, 1911-2007); Ayman Taher; Umm Kulthum, 1898-1975; Tawfik Alhakim, 1898-1987; Museum of Modern Egyptian Art (Cairo, Egypt); Al-Ahram Newspaper (Cairo, Egypt); Ministry of Culture, Egypt
- I. Personal and Professional Papers
  Scope and Contents
  Series I comprises some personal documents such as Salah Taher's birth and death certifications, a few of his passports and identity documents, along with two address books. It also includes assorted professional papers, such as his curriculum vita, minutes of meetings, reports, contracts, as well as other documents such as financial records and pay slips.
  - I. A. Personal Papers, cuid905
  - I. B. Professional Papers, cuid906
  - I. C. Financial Records and Payslips, cuid907
- II. Writings
  Series II comprises writings by Salah Taher and others. It includes the diaries of the artist, handwritten articles and notes, drafts of various articles, as well as scripts for his television show Min ʻĀlam al-Funūn [From the World of the Arts], presented by Sherwet Shafei (b. 1931), then director-general of cultural programs for the state-owned television in the 1970s. The series also includes writings by others about the artist.
  - II. A. Journals and Notes by Salah Taher, cuid908
  - II. B. Draft Texts by Salah Taher, cuid909
  - II. C. Scripts from Min ʻĀlam al-Funūn [From the World of the Arts]
    - 1. "[Botany in the Arts]," November 05, 1964, cuid910
    - 2. "[Cubism]," December 03, 1964, cuid911
    - 3. "[Masterpieces of Surrealism]," December 10, 1964, cuid912
    - 4. "[Nature in Abstract Art]," December 17, 1964, cuid913
    - 5. "[Masterpieces of Abstract Art]," December 31, 1964, cuid914
    - 6. "[Masterpieces of Classical Art]," January 07, 1965, cuid915
    - 7. "[Hanging Rugs from Al Haranīya Village]," January 14, 1965, cuid916
    - 8. "[Masterpieces of Greco-roman Art]," January 28, 1965, cuid917
    - 9. "[Masterpieces of Islamic art]," February 04, 1965, cuid918
    - 10. "[Masterpieces of Persian Art]," February 11, 1965, cuid919
    - 11. "[Masterpieces of Indian art]," February 18, 1965, cuid920
    - 12. "[Masterpieces of Egyptian Art]," February 21, 1965, cuid921
    - 13. "[The Painter Matisse]," February 22, 1965, cuid922
    - 14. "[Chinese Art]," February 25, 1965, cuid923
  - II. D. Writings by Others, cuid924
- III. Correspondence, cuid925
- IV. Exhibition Materials
  Series IV includes exhibition materials such as catalogs and invitations to solo and group exhibitions featuring Salah Taher, one price list, as well as some other exhibition materials.
  - IV. A. Solo Exhibitions
    - 1. "[Exhibition of Salah Taher]," Cairo, 1957., cuid926
    - 2. Fine Arts Gallery, Ministry of Culture and National Guidance, Cairo, 1964., cuid927
    - 3. Galerie Akhenaton, Cairo, 1965., cuid928
    - 4. Teachers' Club, Assiout, 1966., cuid929
    - 5. Cultural Centre for Diplomats, Ministry of Culture, Cairo, 1968., cuid930
    - 6. "[Melody in Form and Music]," Institute of Arabic Music, Cairo, 1968., cuid931
    - 7. Musée des Beaux-Arts et Centre Culturel, Alexandria, 1969., cuid932
    - 8. "Man Outside Time and Place," American University in Cairo, 1971., cuid933
    - 9. "Salah Taher," Safar Khan Art Gallery, Cairo, 1971., cuid934
    - 10. Akhenaton Gallery, Cairo, 1973., cuid935
    - 11. Egyptian Centre for International Cultural Cooperation, Cairo, 1975., cuid936
    - 12. Galerie Aziza, London, 1977., cuid937
    - 13. Egyptian-Greek Friendship Association, Alexandria, 1984., cuid938
    - 14"[Hūa]," Société des Amis de l'Art, Cairo, 1987., cuid939
    - 15. Hotel Pullman Maadi Tower, Cairo, 1990., cuid940
    - 16. Zamalek Art Gallery, Cairo, 2005., cuid941
    - 17. "Salah Taher," Zamalek Art Gallery, Cairo, 2006., cuid942
    - 18. Mohamed Mahmoud Khalil Museum, Cairo, 2008., cuid943
    - 19. "Salah Taher 100 Year Anniversary," Zamalek Art Gallery, 2011., cuid944
    - 20. "Salah Taher," Gezira Art Center, Cairo, 2014., cuid945
    - 21. Library of October 6 University, Cairo, 2016., cuid946
    - 22. "Salah Taher Egyptian Abstractionist," Galerie des Deux Mondes, John F. Kennedy International Airport, New York, undated., cuid947
    - 23. Safar Khan Art Gallery, Cairo, undated., cuid948
  - IV. B. Group Exhibitions
    - 1. Cultural Centre for Diplomats, Ministry of Culture and Information, Cairo, 1972., cuid949
    - 2. Baron Hotel, Cairo, 1992., cuid950
    - 3. "Egypte: Mer et Désert," Centre Culturel Egyptien, Paris, 1997., cuid951
    - 4. "Continuity… Salah Taher and Ayman Taher," Zamalek Art Gallery, Cairo, 2002., cuid952
    - 5. "Mother Egypt," Zamalek Art Gallery, Cairo, 2011., cuid953
  - IV. C. Price Lists, cuid954
  - IV. D. Exhibitions by Others, cuid955
- V. Press Clippings
  Series V covers press clippings of articles written by the artist and published in various newspapers and magazines, spanning from the 1960s to 1989, which he collected and arranged himself. It also includes newspaper articles written by various people and featuring the artist from 1960 to 1989, as well as more recent press clippings featuring the artist from 2000 to 2016.
  - V. A. Press Clippings of Articles Written by Salah Taher
    - 1. Press Clippings from the 1960s, cuid956
    - 2. Press Clippings from the 1970s, cuid957
    - 3. Press Clippings from the 1980s, cuid958
  - V. B. Press Clippings Featuring Salah Taher
    - 1. Press Clippings from the 1960s, cuid959
    - 2. Press Clippings from the 1970s, cuid960
    - 3. Press Clippings from the 1980s, cuid961
    - 4. Press Clippings from the 1990s, cuid962
    - 5. Press Clippings from the 2000s, cuid963
    - 6. Press Clippings from the 2010s, cuid964
    - 7. Undated Press Clippings, cuid965
- VI. Photographic Materials
  Series VI contains photographs, negatives and slides. The images pertain to Salah Taher as an artist, his family life, photographs with several prominent figures, as well as photographs of models, landscapes and people who inspired him. It also includes photographs of his works and exhibition openings, as well as conferences and other gatherings relating to the various positions he held. The photographic negatives and slides were arranged by the artist in individual boxes, and this arrangement has been maintained.
  - VI. A. Photographic Prints
    - 1. Photographs of Salah Taher, cuid966
    - 2. Photographs of the Taher Family, cuid967
    - 3. Photographs from Exhibitions, cuid968
    - 4. Photographs of Salah Taher's Artwork, cuid969
    - 5. Photographs from Conferences and Work Gatherings, cuid970
    - 6. Photographs from Gourna (Luxor), cuid971
    - 7. Photographs of Intellectual Friends of the Artist, cuid972
    - 8. Box 1 of Photographs Arranged by the Artist, cuid973
    - 9. Box 2 of Photographs Arranged by the Artist, cuid974
    - 10. Photographs of Models, cuid975
  - VI. B. Photographic Negatives Arranged by the Artist
    - 1. Box 1, cuid976
    - 2. Box 2, cuid977
    - 3. Box 3, cuid978
    - 4. Box 4, cuid979
    - 5. Box 5, cuid980
  - VI. C. Photographic Slides Arranged by the Artist
    - 1. Box 1, cuid981
    - 2. Box 2, cuid982
    - 3. Box 3, cuid983
- VII: Other Items in the Possession of the Artist, cuid984